Okay, so today's דף daf is ק"ט Kuf Tet and we start
a little bit back on ק"ח עמוד ב', Kuf Chet Amud Bet,
the two dots before the משנה, mishna, רצה יביא בדמיהם שנים. Ratza
yavi bidmeihem shenayim. So this is about if somebody says transferring the
קדושה, kedusha, he sanctified one animal and now he's transferring the קדושה,
kedusha, he can bring with the same money two animals for an
עולה olah etc. אמר רב מנשיא בר זביד אמר רב, Amar Rav
Menashya bar Zavid amar Rav, לא שנו אלא דאמר שור זה עולה.
Lo shanu ela de-amar shor zeh olah. All of this is when
you say this ox is an עולה, olah, so the קדושה kedusha
goes to the animal and if the animal gets a מום mum
you transfer it and then it can go to any other thing
that you're going to use for an עולה olah even if it's
not, as we said, even if it's not the same מין, min,
even if it's not the same number. אבל אמר שור זה עלי
עולה, Aval amar shor zeh alai olah, if you say I take
upon me the obligation to bring this ox, הוקבע, hukva, then it
gets fixed, presumably it gets fixed that you have to bring one
and you have to bring one ox, so then it becomes a
personal obligation, not just sanctifying the thing, and if the thing gets
a מום, mum, then you have to transfer the קדושה kedusha similarly
to one ox and you don't have any alternative. So the גמרא
Gemara is not happy with this. The גמרא Gemara says ודילמא עלי
להביאו קאמר? Ve-dilma alai lehavio ka-amar? No, nevertheless, even if you say
on me, you're really here bridging two types of statements. The normal
statement is this ox is an עולה olah or I obligate myself
to bring an ox as an עולה. olah. But if you said
I obligate myself to bring this ox as an עולה, olah, so
if the ox gets a מום, mum, you can't bring this ox
that has a מום, mum, so once I can't bring this ox,
I can transfer the קדושה kedusha to two sheep or to two
oxen or whatever. So saying the on me doesn't change things as
long as you're still saying this ox because once it gets a
מום mum you don't have any alternative, you can't bring it anyway.
So maybe עלי להביאו alai lehavio to bring it and this particular
one קאמר, ka-amar, אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. ela i itamar hachi
itamar. What's said here is how it was said: אמר רב מנשיא
בר זביד אמר רב, Amar Rav Menashya bar Zavid amar Rav, לא
שנו אלא דאמר שור זה עולה. Lo shanu ela de-amar shor zeh
olah. When is this true that if it gets a מום mum
you can bring some variation? So if you say this ox is
an עולה, olah, אי נמי, i nami, or even if you say
אמר שור זה עלי עולה Amar shor zeh alai olah on me,
but as long as you're saying this ox, once it gets a
מום mum you're not able to satisfy it, so then you transfer
the קדושה kedusha and it can be on two oxen, on three
sheep, on whatever you want.
You don't directly transfer, you first redeem it with money and then
use the money. אבל אמר שור זה ודמיו עלי עולה, Aval amar
shor zeh u-damav alai olah, but let's say you said not just
this ox, this ox and the value of this ox I accept
upon myself an obligation to bring as an עולה olah and presumably
as a single ox עולה, olah, then הוקבע, hukva, then it's fixed.
So then if the animal gets a מום, mum, since you accepted
on yourself an obligation to bring with the value an ox as
an עולה, olah, then you can't transfer the קדושה kedusha to like
two sheep or to two oxen or whatever because now you've not
only sanctified the thing, you've taken upon yourself an obligation to bring
a similar קורבן korban with the money and if this קורבן korban
can't be brought you have to transfer it to a similar thing,
to a single ox. Okay, so that's the end of the last
משנה. mishna. Now we go on to obviously related but a different
topic. So let's look at the next משנה. mishna. האומר אחד מכבשי
הקדש ואחד משורי הקדש, Ha-omer echad mi-kivsai hekdesh ve-echad mi-shorai hekdesh, one
of my sheep is going to be הקדש, hekdesh, I sanctify one
of my sheep, and of course you were not nice enough to
tell us which one, or I sanctify one of my oxen. היו
לו שנים הגדול שבהן הקדש. Hayu lo shenayim ha-gadol she-ba-hen hekdesh. If
you have two, you assume that you meant, since you're giving something
to הקדש, hekdesh, we interpret what you're saying and assume what you're
saying you mean the bigger gift. So we assume you gave the
bigger ox and the bigger sheep, presumably bigger means more expensive although
that's not so clear. היו לו שלשה, Hayu lo shlosha, let's say
you have three oxen or three sheep and you said one of
my oxen, you didn't say which one, so which do we assume
you mean? בינוני שבהן הקדש, Beinoni she-ba-hen hekdesh, the middle one. Always
order on a date from the middle of the menu, right? So
not too expensive, not too cheap. So that's a little bit strange
because right now we assume if we assume you mean the more
expensive, then why don't we say here's the most expensive? Obviously a
reasonable interpretation is we would not we're assuming that you'll give the
best to הקדש, hekdesh, but we're assuming you won't give the worst.
Okay, so if we assume you won't give the worst, if you
only have two you'll give the top, if you have three you'll
give the middle. But we'll see how the גמרא gemara deals with
it. Let's say you say פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי, Perashti ve-eini
yodea mah perashti, I said explicitly which sheep I would give or
which ox I would give, but I forget which one and you
have three of them, so what are you going to do, have
to give all three? או שאמר לי אבא, O she-amar li abba,
or my father told me on his deathbed that he had sanctified
one of his sheep or one of his oxen and he died
and I don't know which one he was doing, ואיני יודע מה,
ve-eini yodea mah, I don't know which one, הגדול שבהן הקדש. ha-gadol
she-ba-hen hekdesh. So you assume that if you specified or your father
specified or whatever that he was talking he gave the most expensive
one. Now that's a real problem to the first half of the
משנה mishna because if you assume that a person when they're going
to specify normally will say well people will more be inclined to
give their most expensive if they're already sanctifying something, so when they
don't specify also we should assume he means the most expensive and
not the middle one. So what's the meaning of this? So let's
see what the גמרא gemara says.
And also why don't we just say that you should bring the
top two? Let's say we'll move to that. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. gemara. אלמא, alma, we see from the first
line of the משנה mishna that if you have two we assume
you meant the biggest one, מקדיש בעין יפה מקדיש, makdish be-ayin yafa
makdish, somebody who sanctifies sanctifies with a generous eye. The most expensive
and not the middle one. So what, how, what's the meaning of
this? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Right. And also,
why don't we just say that he should bring the top two,
let's say?
Well, okay, we'll move to that. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says אלמא, Alma, we see
from the first line of the משנה Mishna that if you have
two, we assume he meant the biggest one. מקדיש בעין יפה, Makdish
ba'ayin yafa, מקדיש, Makdish, somebody who sanctifies, sanctifies with a generous eye.
Or either we, again
with all these things as we've seen in a lot of the
recent משניות, Mishnayos, we've tried to interpret your statement. We didn't really
ask you what you were thinking. We sort of are going to
choose how to interpret your statement. So here too, it's a question
of when we say something like somebody who sanctifies does it with
a generous eye, are we really making a statement of psychology or
are we making sort of a legal statement of how we're going
to choose to interpret what your statements mean in the context of
הקדש? hekdesh? But either way, we're going to interpret it to mean
the more generous one. אימא סיפא: Aima seifa: so how about the
second case? Path three? בינונית שבהקדש, Beinonit shebahekdesh, the middle one. אלמא
מקדיש בעין רעה מקדיש. Alma makdish b'ayin ra makdish. Somebody who sanctifies
does it with a stingy eye, or at least a not super
generous eye. So how do you explain the first case and the
middle case? אמר שמואל: Amar Shmuel: חיישינן אף לבינונית, chaishinan af l'beinonit,
דלגבי קטן עין יפה הוא. d'lgabei katan ayin yafa hu. You're right.
And this is going to help us with the end case of
the משנה. Mishna. When it says the middle, it doesn't mean we
assume that we definitely assume that you meant the middle one. We
assume it's possible you meant the middle one because the middle one
is at least more generous than the lowest valued one. So we
assume that we're going to interpret your statements to be a more
generous statement, but we're not going to assume that necessarily means the
most generous. As long as it's a generous type of a statement.
So when there are three, it's possible you meant the middle, it's
possible you meant the top. Okay, so we're going to re-read the
משנה. Mishna. So let's see what you do.
Okay, so היכי עביד? heichi avid? How do you handle this situation
where it's uncertain whether you meant the middle or the top? אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא: Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba: ממתין לו עד
שיומם. mamtin lo ad sheyumam. You wait till the middle one gets
a blemish, and maybe you put it in a circumstance that would
encourage that.
ומחליה לקדושתיה אגדול. umeichalei lekdushatia agadol. And you transfer the קדושה kedusha
to the big one. You say if I had meant, or if
my words mean, because presumably you don't know what you meant, if
my words meant the middle one, then it now has a blemish,
I transfer its קדושה kedusha to the big one, and I'm going
to bring the big one.
If my words meant the big one, then there's no purpose of
this transferring anyway, and then in the end you just bring the
big one. So you bring the big one because you bring the
one that is the most generous to bring, but in case you
possibly meant the middle, you wait for it to get
a
blemish and you redeem it and then you're going to bring the
big one. Although that's completely absent from the משנה. Mishna. Okay.
So it's basically the same thing as end case.
Sort of, except the end case does not discuss transferring the קדושה,
kedusha, so we'll have to see about how we bridge the gap.
We're getting closer to bridging the gap between all these three. Okay,
so let's take a look. What?
תפוס למרוע Tofas limrua you can always change.
Well, the problem is that you can't do it as direct exchange
because the Torah says by the prohibition of תמורה: tmura: לא ימיר
אותו טוב ברע ורע בטוב. lo yamir oto tov b'ra ve-ra b'tov.
And רע בטוב ra b'tov is understood by the גמרא Gemara as
even a מום mum with a non-בעל מום. baal mum. So you
cannot directly transfer the קדושה. kedusha. The phrase here in the גמרא
Gemara is a little bit is a little bit imprecise. You can't
directly transfer the קדושה kedusha from one animal to another, even from
a בעל מום baal mum to a non-בעל מום. baal mum. You
have to redeem it with money and then transfer from the money
to the animal. Okay, but yes, but that you can do because
we're saying it's possible you meant the middle case. Okay, now let's
keep on going on the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה: Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar Avuha: לא שנו אלא
דאמר אחד משורי הקדש. lo shanu ela d'amar echad mishvarai hekdesh. It
said one of my oxen. That's where we don't know if he
means the middle or the top and you do this like trick
or covering your bases. אבל אמר שור בשורי הקדש, aval amar shor
bishvarai hekdesh, an ox from my oxen, not just one of my
oxen but an ox from my oxen, הגדול שבהן הקדש. hagedol shebahen
hekdesh. Then you mean the most expensive one. Why? תורא בתוראי קאמר.
Torah b'torai ka'amar. You mean the best of my oxen, the choice
ox of my oxen. So if you say one of them, we
don't know which one. But if you say an ox from my
oxen, you mean like the best ox from my oxen. Okay, now
איני eini says the גמרא. Gemara. Is this really so? והא אמר
רב הונא אמר רבי חייא משמיה דעולא: veha Amar Rav Huna Amar
Rabbi Chiya mishmeih d'Ulla: האומר לחברו בית בביתי אני מוכר לך. ha'omer
l'chavero bayit b'battay ani mocher lach.
If you said to somebody I will sell you a house amongst
my houses, not just one of my houses but a house amongst
my houses, then מראהו עלייה, mareihu alaiya,
you can say okay I meant the attic. Because the attic is
considered a בית. bayit. We would think a בית bayit means the
whole house, but a floor is considered to also be it. And
we're assuming that the attic is the less preferable because you don't
have direct access to the ground level. So the point of this
seems to be that you can choose which of your things that
fall into the category of houses, you don't have to give the
best, you can even assume it means the worst. So how come
we interpret this way? Now of course it's possible that maybe we
have a different standard of how to interpret your words in the
context of commerce than we do in context of הקדש. hekdesh. We'll
get to that eventually, but the גמרא Gemara is not yet assuming
that. Now I want also to say a point about how it's
possible that there is this misrepresentation that there's this question about what
you mean. If we were dealing with מטלטלין, metaltelin, chattel, then classic
chattel is transferred through some type of physical possessing of the object.
You do משיכה, meshicha, you draw it, you do הגבהה, hagba'a, you
lift it. If you transfer money and the object isn't taken into
possession, it actually the sale is not final by movable objects. By
land it's not that way. By land and by slaves and so
on, the transfer is done either through money or through a שטר,
shtar, through a writ. So those types of things, the thing doesn't
have to be in front of you, so it's possible you described
it and then you realize hey there's ambiguity in this contract, which
one were you referring to? And that's why these issues come up
particularly in the context of the sale of real estate. Okay, so
anyway here we do not interpret it to mean the best one.
So the גמרא Gemara says
לאו משום lav mishum isn't that not because
דגריע ליה? degaria leh? Did I skip a line?
לאו משום דגריע, lav mishum degaria, isn't it because the עליה Aliyah
is the worst and you can say that it means the worst,
not the best? So לא מעולה שבבתים, lo meulah shebebatim, עליה Aliyah
here does not mean the attic, עליה Aliyah here means the best,
which is a very you know strange, sometimes עליה Aliyah does mean
the best, especially if we're talking about like different qualities of land
and a field. But in the context of houses עליה Aliyah you
know almost always means
the roof level, the attic level, but here we're saying it means
no no it means the best.
So you mean עליה Aliyah means my best house?
Yeah, but we're not done, we're not going to stick with that.
What I would have thought you would have said is that you
know you're trying to just impress the guy, I have so many
houses, you know, like I'm a big company, you should rent from
me in the future kind of thing, that's why I'm saying I'm
selling you one of my houses in case you ever have some
other needs.
Okay, but still the bottom line is which one do you get?
No, what I'm saying meaning you should be able to give me
any one you want. That's what I would have thought, that's what
he's trying to say.
Well, we'll see anyway. I mean the גמרא Gemara is going to
talk at the end about a difference between sale and הקדש. hekdesh.
Let's take a look. מתיבי. Meisive. שור בשורי הקדש וכן שור של
הקדש שנתערב באחרים. shor beshvarai hekdesh u'khein shor shel hekdesh shenitarav be'acherin.
So let's say you say I am sanctifying an ox amongst my
oxen or one of my oxen is הקדש hekdesh and it got
mixed up and I can't identify which one I have sanctified. So
what do you do? הגדול שבהן הקדש. hagadol shebehen hekdesh. So the
biggest one you give to הקדש hekdesh because then obviously you're giving
the most expensive. Of course the problem is it's very nice that
it's the most expensive but maybe it's not the one you meant,
or maybe it's not the one you sanctified. What if the other
animal is still at large and mixed up, or it's the other
one that you meant? So here's how you cover your bases, like
what the גמרא Gemara said before. וכולן ימכרו לצרכי עולות ודמיהן חולין.
vekulan yimachru letzorchei olot u'demeihen chulin.
So what I do is, let's say one of my oxen get
mixed up with ten others and I don't know which one I
sanctified. So I bring the biggest one. Now, that's very nice I'm
bringing the biggest one, but let's say I sanctified a medium sized
one. So I go ahead and I know that Charlie here has
been dying to bring nine עולות olot to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. I sell him all of those things, I take the money,
he is going to bring all of those as קורבנות. korbanot. So
even if my עולה olah was among the other nine, I know
that he's going to bring them as קורבנות. korbanot. So I know
it's going to be brought. I'm not going to wind up using
it in my field. He's going to use it. Now the money
Charlie gives me I can actually pocket for my own use. Why?
Because in the I'm not transferring the קדושה. kedushah. When can I
not use the proceeds? If somehow you're trying to transfer the קדושה
kedushah away from the animal. But I'm not trying to transfer the
קדושה kedushah away from the animal, right? The animal remains הקדש hekdesh
and I'm just selling you all of these and even the one
that might be a קורבן korban among them for your own use,
so we're not transferring קדושה kedushah so I can use all of
the money and he's going to bring all of them as קורבנות.
korbanot. So I'm going to bring the best one in case I
meant it, and if I didn't mean the best one, they're all
going to get brought anyway. So that's what it says. Okay. וכולן
ימכרו לצרכי עולות. vekulan yimachru letzorchei olot.
All of the rest of them are sold for the sake of
עולות olot because I was sanctifying here an עולה, olah, ודמיהן חולין
udemeihen chulin and I can use the money. Anyway you see that
we don't interpret when I say an ox from my oxen, we
don't say definitely means the best, we say maybe it means the
best. So תרגמא אשור של הקדש שנתערב באחרים. targumah ashor shel hekdesh
shenitarav be'acherin.
No, when it says that I don't know and I'm not sure
and I have to use all of them for a קורבן, korban,
that's when one got mixed up. But the first case which when
I say an ox among the oxen, then I only then I
mean the best and I don't have to worry about the rest.
So the גמרא Gemara says והא הכא נמי קאמר, vehacha nami ka'amar,
it says but it equates the two. When I said an ox
amongst my oxen and the case when I got it mixed up.
So the same way when I got mixed up I might have
meant the others, presumably the ox among the oxen I might have
meant the others. So the גמרא Gemara says no, תרגמא אגדול. targumah
agadol. No, they're similar in that in both cases I bring the
biggest one. But they're different that when I said an ox among
the oxen I end by bringing the biggest one. When one gets
mixed up, not only do I bring the biggest one, I have
to sell the rest to be used for עולות. olot. Okay, so
that we got out of that. That was not so elegant but
we still have the bigger problem about the case of the house
of the house where it really seems it's a different standard and
that's what we turn to now. מתיבי Meisive I'll ask you on
this. בית בביתי אני מוכר לך, bayit beveiti ani mocher lach, I
am selling you a house amongst my houses. ונפל venafal and now
I have ten houses and one of them collapsed before you came
to get your house.
מראהו נפול, mar'eihu naful,
I say oh that was the one I sold you. Which basically
means that I have the right since it was not specified to
determine which one I meant.
Okay. עבד בעבדי אני מוכר לך, eved be'avadai ani mocher lach, I'm
selling you one of my slaves. Again something that doesn't have to
be done with the slave present, could be done by a שטר.
shtar. ומת u'meis and one of my slaves died. מראהו מת, mar'eihu
meis, oh that was the one I meant. The sale took place.
The money was transferred or even if the money wasn't transferred, I
now have a you know document of sale and I can and
I can go ahead and I can go ahead and collect the
money. All you have is proof that you own it but it's
ambiguous which one you owned. So the principle here is even more
than just we interpret it to mean the worst because obviously it
wasn't the worst at the time. So it was really a question
of interpreting what the intent and we somehow assumed worst, we would
have assumed what what it would have meant at that time. And
really what it means is that any, it's a different principle which
is any ambiguity of terms it is the seller's right to determine
what they mean. Okay, so that's a principle which we'll see in
a minute, it'll be, we'll see the phrase that articulates that. ואמאי
ve-amai why do you give him the worst? לחזי היי דנפל והיי
דמת le-chezei hai denafal vehai demes let's see which one collapsed and
which one died, and couldn't you, we should interpret the phrase of
an ox am-, a house among my house to mean what was
the best at the time. לוקח? lokeiach? So the גמרא Gemara for
for now finally switches, it says okay there are different standards. לוקח
אמרת? lokeiach amarta? One minute, you're talking about a purchase? שאני לוקח
דיד בעל השטר על התחתונה. shani lokeiach de-yad ba'al hashtar al hatachtona.
When it comes to a purchase, the the owner of the document,
meaning the one who is using the document to purchase, the one,
the purchaser, always has the short end of the stick in interpreting
the terms. And the reason is is because until now this has
been my property, you are the one basically coming to make a
claim. You're trying to say, oh no this term here means your
big house not your small house. You are trying to extract from
me. It is known that I sold, but it's not known what
I sold. So you're always seen as the one that's trying to
make a claim against me to determine which house or which slave
I meant. And therefore you have the burden of proof to mean
that it means a better one. If I claim that it means
the one that happens to have died and you can't prove otherwise,
then you're stuck with that. So this is actually a very important
principle in contract law as you could imagine and bills of sale
that that's why you really have to keep all the terms as
as very very clear because the person who's coming to make demands
is the one that has the burden of proof and else we
could always interpret it to be the least. That is different from
how we interpret the phrases in the context of
הקדש. hekdesh. השתא דאתית להכי, hashta de-asit le-hachi, now when you say
that אפילו תימא עליה afilu teima aliya even in the earlier case
of showing him the attic, דגריעא degreia and the attic is worse
than the ground floor why? Because יד בעל השטר על התחתונה. yad
ba'al hashtar al hatachtona. The power of the one holding the document,
meaning trying to use the document to extract, always has the weaker,
always is always on the bottom. So therefore by הקדש, hekdesh, now
again this is shows you that these are much more about sort
of decisions about legally how we're going to choose to interpret than
trying to get at your deepest intention. I mean you could maybe
have said no no no by הקדש hekdesh because everybody we assume
everybody is always so generous we're going to assume the intentions are
different than in the case of sale. It's possible. But I think
that it's clear that the גמרא Gemara here is moving more to
a question about no, how as a matter of law are we
going to choose to interpret. So when it comes to trying to
transfer property and trying to demand property from somebody else, we're going
to say the burden of proof is on the one extracting the
property and any ambiguity is interpreted in the favor of the person
that started with the property. And in the case of הקדש hekdesh
we're going to choose to interpret it as as a generous statement,
but it's interesting because of the case about the three in the
middle, we're not necessarily going to say it's definitely the most generous.
It's something that is that is at least some degree of generosity,
it's not the worst. So in the case of three it might
be the middle, it might be the top. Yes Gary.
I'm surprised that anyone would think that הקדש hekdesh would be treated
the same as a ordinary sale property because if I want to
sell you my ox, you have to do something to create a
קנין kinyan like pulling it into your domain whereas if I say
this is this ox is an עולה, olla, that's it. Now הקדש
hekdesh doesn't have the you the priest doesn't have to come and
and do anything.
So you're saying that part of the reason that it's better is
because in a way הקדש hekdesh is no longer in the position
of having to extract. Right. So that's a good point, of course
the question still being that there's an ambiguity which one you meant,
so it's not like but it's an interesting point to use the
principle which is a principle that we say that כל היכא דאיכא
בי גזא דרחמנא איכא, kol heicha de-ika be-gaza de-rachmana ika, that
that whatever it is it's in the possession of הקדש hekdesh and
another phrase that's relevant to that is what do you call it
is that דבריו כמיסורין ונתונין דמי dvarav kimsurin venesunin dami that when
you speak and verbally give something that it's like you've already given
it over. So that's an interesting possibility that maybe that also is
why we're going to choose to interpret it in the favor of
הקדש. hekdesh. Now it doesn't explain the middle case which is when
you're ambiguous and there are three that you mean two or three
and we don't just say we're going to choose to mean two.
Also just one last comment about the last case in the משנה,
mishna, the last case in the משנה mishna is when when is
when there was a specific one said and you didn't remember which
one was said. So that actually points to the difference between trying
to get at what you really meant and interpreting what you said.
In the case where your father said something and you don't know
what he meant, he said one but you have no idea. There's
no there's no text to interpret, right? We don't know what the
text was. The father died. Or you said something but you don't
know what. There's no text to interpret. The text was explicit. It's
just forgotten what you said. So there really is a question of
trying to get at the bottom of what was probably said. So
when we're asking ourselves the question what was probably said, we'll say
well if people are giving something to הקדש hekdesh they're probably giving
the nicest thing. And that's why in the last case when you
don't remember what you said, but your father said something and he
died and we just the question is well what probably was said
was so then we'll say oh well we'll assume people meant the
best thing. That's the last case. However when we know what was
said, but we don't know how to interpret it. When you said
one of my oxen and we don't know how to interpret it,
there we allow for the fact that maybe, you know, we don't—we
should not interpret it maximally because, again, this points to—it's a little
ironic, you would think, oh, well, we can choose to say it
means the best. Yes, we can, but part of the point here
also is, and this we've seen in previous משניות, mishnayot, it's not
just what you're thinking, it's also what you said.
Although we make two of them essentially.
I mean, wait, let me finish my sentence. So although when we
try to guess if you said something specific, we assume that you
probably meant the best, here we know what you said and you
didn't say the best. You said an ambiguous statement. So therefore, we're
trying to, like, straddle the difference. On the one hand, we assume
you're trying to do the best. On the other hand, you didn't
say the best. So we'll interpret it in a way that, you
know, at least bridges that, at least doesn't mean the worst, but
doesn't necessarily mean the absolute best, and covers all those possibilities and
that was the middle case. No, when there's three, we say it
means either two or three, we
don't know which one.
Didn't we say that שמואל
חושש אף לבינוני,
Shmuel
hoshesh
af l'veinoni, which basically means that you bring the nicest one and
you attach—that's the result.
But the first stage of interpretation is, if we don't say it
means the best, we say it means something that is better than
the worst. And therefore we're not sure, and it could mean anything
between, you know, x minus one all the way to x, as
long as it's not the worst. Okay. The result is you bring
the best, but that's different than how we're interpreting it, because you
have to now wait for the whole מום. mum. Okay. Did you
have a question Charlie? No? Okay fine. All right, so anyway, what
is interesting about this is that I do think that this points
to a theme that we've been seeing for a while, is the
difference between, you know, if you remember we had all these crazy
cases where somebody said, I'm a נזיר Nazir from dates, right, and
you know, made these things which are these hybrids where it really
became a question of not so much, I mean, to some degree
to mediate between a debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel or בית
שמאי, Beit Shammai, but really an emphasis on trying to, you know,
bracket what you're thinking and say what do we do with the
words. So here, although you could have said if we have the
words let's choose to interpret it maximally, we're choosing to say no
there's some ambiguity and they just don't mean the minimal but they
don't necessarily mean the maximal. But if you said something we don't
know, then we're going to assume that you as you said the
most maximal statement.
Because—yeah, I mean, I'm just not getting it, because in the case
where you said one of my oxen,
yeah, you know what you said,
we know what you said, and we should just be able to
guess
what—first of all, it's not so clear what you said. I don't
know, I wasn't really thinking. I said one, I wasn't thinking specifically
which one. And number two becomes a question of do we care
what you said, and that goes back to בית הלל Beit Hillel
and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. If you remember בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says I don't really care what you were
thinking, I care what you said.
Right, so he said one, so then just pick whichever one you
want.
No, so then we have a legal question. How do I interpret
one? How do I interpret an ambiguous statement?
But then say that what most people think is the best one,
so then just say that's the best one.
Or let's say that at least we should interpret that if it's
not explicit, we'll interpret it to mean not the minimum but everything
else that's within the possibilities.
But what I'm saying is if you take two of them together,
it's still just the best one. Because if most people think the
best one and he said one of them, then just say that's
the best one.
That's if you only went by intention, not if you go by
the actual statement. But if the statement doesn't necessarily allow for that
or point specifically in that direction, then the statement is more ambiguous
and we're going to interpret it with its ambiguity rather than make
it more specific if it's not fundamentally a specific statement. All right,
let's move on. Okay, next משנה. mishna. הרי עלי עולה יקריבנה
במקדש Harei alai olah yakrivenah b'Mikdash ואם הקריבה בבית חוניו לא יצא.
v'im
hikrivah b'Veit Honyo lo yatza.
הרי עלי עולה יקריבנה במקדש. Harei alai olah yakrivenah b'Mikdash. Somebody says
I'll bring an עולה, olah, so obviously you bring it in the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. ואם הקריבה בבית חוניו לא יצא. v'im hikrivah
b'Veit Honyo lo yatza. Now here something gets thrown in totally like
a curveball.
There was this בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, this alternate central place of
worship in Alexandria in Egypt, which is called a בית חוניו. Beit
Honyo. I think we actually even know about this from Philo or
Josephus.
I think we do. Anyway, it was called בית חוניו Beit Honyo
and it says if you bring it there
you're not יוצא. yotzei. First of all, you're also over on the
biblical prohibition of שחוטי חוץ, shichutei chutz, bringing קרבנות korbanot outside the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but in addition to that, you're also not
יוצא yotzei your vow. Okay, now all of that is relatively obvious,
but let's take a look at the next line which is pretty
fascinating. הרי עלי עולה שיקריבנה בבית חוניו. Harei alai olah she'yakrivenah b'Veit
Honyo. I accept upon myself an עולה olah that I'll bring in
בית חוניו. Beit Honyo. So there you go again about making a
statement and how much is it going to be what you said.
Okay, how much are we going to interpret that literally? יקריבנה במקדש.
yakrivenah b'Mikdash. Bring it in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and then
you'll be יוצא. yotzei. We're basically going to ignore the end of
your statement which is an impossibility halakhically. ואם הקריבה בבית חוניו יצא.
v'im hikrivah b'Veit Honyo yatza. But if you brought it in בית
חוניו, Beit Honyo, יצא. yatza. Now you have—you've done a prohibition but
you fulfilled your vow. You did what you said you were going
to do, so you fulfilled your vow. So even though you've done
a prohibitive act that you're חייב כרת chayav karet and it doesn't
count as a קרבן, korban, but you did your vow. Now the
גמרא Gemara is going to say you didn't even do your vow
because you said you're going to bring it as a sacrifice and
what you do outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash doesn't count as
a sacrifice.
Well, what he meant is...
Okay, well by
the way, this temple, this community that built that מקדש, Mikdash, it
was a large community. So they basically...
the most well the most generous read that the גמרא Gemara is
going to have or that the תנאים Tannaim have is that it's
a בית—it's Beit a place of worship to God but it's still
outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. There was another body of
opinion that it was actually a place of idolatry.
So this is right, this is a pretty soft משנה mishna considering
everything, it sounds
like...
Right, right, right. I mean the גמרא Gemara gets harsher statements, but
this משנה Mishnah doesn't even say הרי זה יצא וחייב כרת. Harey
ze yatza v'chayav kares. Right, it doesn't even say that. Now we'll
see some of that, we'll see some of that in the גמרא,
Gemara, but this משנה Mishnah is very soft considering that. Now the
next משנה Mishnah you'll have more of a critique, but this משנה
Mishnah is pretty soft. רבי שמעון אומר אין זה עולה. Rabbi Shimon
omer ein ze olah. No, not an עולה olah at all, it's
outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You didn't fulfill your obligation.
הריני נזיר, Hareini nazir, somebody vows a נזיר, nazir, and at the
end of the נזירות neziros is over, יגלח במקדש, yigaleach be-Mikdash, go
to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ואם גילח בבית חוניו ולא יצא,
V'im gileach be-Beis Chonyo v'lo yatza, doesn't work in בית חוניו Beis
Chonyo obviously because that's not a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. הריני נזיר
שגילח בבית חוניו, Hareini nazir she-gileach be-Beis Chonyo, you stipulate that you'll
end your נזירות neziros through the rituals and you'll do them in
the בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, יגלח במקדש, yigaleach be-Mikdash, nevertheless you're in
the מקדש. Mikdash. ואם גילח בבית חוניו יצא, V'im gileach be-Beis Chonyo
yatza, but you do it if you did in בית חוניו, Beis
Chonyo, which is crazy because
how do
you end
your נזירות? neziros? There's only one way to end your נזירות, neziros,
which is bringing the right קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. So in the other case you could say you fulfilled your
vow but you were חייב כרת, chayav kares, but here, how does
it end your נזירות neziros if it's not the legitimate מקדש? Mikdash?
רבי שמעון אומר אין זה נזיר. Rabbi Shimon omer ein ze Nazir.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, the whole thing is absurd, you
cannot make a stipulation like that and it's not a נזירות neziros
at all. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon makes sense, but the חכמים
Chachamim position is a little bizarre. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. He may be saying it's absurd.
He may be saying as a way of getting out like many
rabbis will say if you were married in a conservative ceremony or
a reform, you don't need a גט get because...
okay, but he still needs the mechanics. Fine, it might be motivated
by that, but you still need the mechanics, the mechanics of saying
you're not a נזיר nazir is because...
but he may not be saying it's absurd.
Okay, but the mechanics, I understand what you're saying in terms of
the motivation, but the mechanics to say that it's not binding are
still that you cannot make a binding vow about a קרבן korban
relating to a קרבן korban in בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo. Okay, fine.
Charlie.
I was just going to say maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
saying he hasn't said anything, it's like me making a vow to
eat חמץ chametz on פסח.
Pesach. Well, that's what I sort of meant by absurd. Okay, alright.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. יצא. Yatza. So the
גמרא Gemara first questions the חכמים Chachamim that say if you bring
your קרבן korban in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo you're יצא. yotze. המיסת
קטליה, Hamistokadla, you murdered it or slaughtered it, meaning it's not a
קרבן korban if you bring a קרבן korban outside of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You can't say well, okay, maybe you were עובר
עבירה oveir aveyra but it was still a קרבן. korban. It wasn't
a קרבן, korban, it's you know, if you slaughter something which is
sanctified outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's not a קרבן korban
at all. אמר רב המנונא, Amar Rav Hamnuna, נעשה כאומר הרי עלי
עולה על מנת שלא אתחייב באחריותה. Na'aseh k'omer harey alay olah al
mnas shelo etchayev beachrayuta. Okay, so what we do is we interpret
your statement in the way that allows it to be binding, and
we basically say like this, when you say I'm going to bring
an עולה olah to bring it in בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, we
don't say that I'm going to bring a קרבן korban in בית
חוניו, Beis Chonyo, it doesn't count הלכתית halachically as a קרבן. korban.
What you say is, I'm going to bring an, I'm going to
sanctify an עולה, olah, I plan on bringing it in בית חוניו,
Beis Chonyo, the consequence being that after I bring it in בית
חוניו Beis Chonyo and slaughter it, and I know הלכתית halachically that
doesn't constitute bringing a קרבן, korban, but after that I am free
from any obligation to bring a substitute. Right, when normally if I
say I accept an עולה olah and then I sanctify
an
animal and it dies, I still have to bring an עולה. olah.
But here since I've made clear my intent to bring it in
בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, what I'm actually saying is if I go
through the act of bringing it in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo even
though הלכה halacha doesn't recognize that as a bringing of a קרבן,
korban, that is the limit of my vow. Okay, so we interpret
your vow to sort of say yes, what you're trying to do
is bring this in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo and after that not
be obligated and we'll interpret it in that way, okay, even though
it is not really a קרבן. korban. Okay, so then, so then
the difference between the חכמים Chachamim and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, you said קרבן, korban, you can't
have a קרבן korban in בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, it's not binding.
Okay, whereas the חכמים Chachamim say yes, but we're going to reinterpret
the word קרבן korban in a way that makes the vow as
close as possible to be similar to what his, to his meaning.
Okay, so we're trying to you know go through all these hoops
for someone who's like doing it in a...
exactly.
So anyway, but because you're sort of saying I'm able to do
it in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo and there my obligation stops, doesn't
say that we also say that the first part of the משנה
Mishnah that if you bring it in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
you're יצא, yotze, because you're not saying I'm only going to satisfy
my vow by bringing it in בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, we're interpreting
to say that if I do bring it in בית חוניו Beis
Chonyo my obligation ends there. Okay, so that's the statement. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר ליה רבא, Amar ley Rava, so
רבא Rava said back to רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna that gave this
answer, אלא מעתה סיפא דקתני הריני נזיר שגילח בבית חוניו יגלח במקדש,
Ela me-ata seifa diktani hareyini nazir she-gileach be-Beis Chonyo yigaleach be-Mikdash, so
the case of the נזיר nazir who wants to do it in
בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, ואם גילח בבית חוניו יצא, v'im gileach be-Beis
Chonyo yatza, you do it in the מקדש Mikdash and if you
did in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo you're done and your נזירות neziros
is over, היכי דמי, heichi dami, how could that, how could that
work? דנעשה כאומר הריני נזיר על מנת שלא אתחייב באחריות קרבנותיו. D'na'aseh
k'omer hareyini nazir al mnas shelo etchayev beachrayus korbanosav. That I am
a נזיר, nazir, I am a נזיר nazir but I will not
be obligated in bringing my sacrifices if I happen to bring them
in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo my obligation of sacrifices ends there. So
the גמרא Gemara says it's very nice that you're trying to free
yourself from your sacrifice obligation, but your נזירות neziros doesn't end until
you do the right thing. So it's not just about your personal
obligation. נזיר, Nazir, for a נזיר, nazir, כמה דלא מייתי קרבנותיו לא
מיתכשר, kama d'lo maysei korbanosav lo miskasher, as long as you don't
bring your קרבנות korbanos the right way, לא מיתכשר, lo miskasher, you're
not fit, meaning your status doesn't change. So here you can't just
interpret it as we're going to reread your vow. Even if we
allow you and say you don't have an obligation of sacrifices because
you did this, you still can't change your status. if you haven't
done them the right way. So how do you explain this case
of the משנה? Mishna? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר. Amar. So
אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, here's what really how we interpret
your statement. אדם זה לדורו נתכוון. Adam zeh lidoro niskaven. This person
is trying to give a gift to God. He just is a
little confused and he thinks that בית חוניו Beis Chonyo is a
legitimate way of doing it. I mean you could imagine the phenomenon,
right? I mean if you have a very active מקדש Mikdash central
place of worship or sacrifices in Alexandria, and by the way, you
know, particularly that was well known to the diaspora Jews, which were
not always very learned, and they're very aware that this is where
Jews bring sacrifices. So you could be very innocently trying to bring
a קרבן Korban and thinking this is legitimate, and you know all
your friends that have gone there, and that's what you're trying to
do. So that so you're trying to give a gift and you
think this is legitimate, I mean a sacrifice gift. אמר Amar and
what we you said, or what we interpret what you're saying is
the following: אי סגי בבית חוניו, Isadye beBeis Chonyo, if it works
as a sacrifice in בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, טרחנא, tarachna, then I'll
go to the effort, cause that's close to me, I live in,
you know, I live in Egypt, wherever I live, if it works
in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo I'll bring it to, then I'm intending
to give it. טפי, Tfei, if I have to schlep all the
way to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, לא מצינא לאיצטעורי, lo matzina l'itztruye, I don't
want to I don't want to go to all that schlep. So
that's actually a reasonable read. When you say I'm going to bring
it in בית חוניו, Beis Chonyo, we read it to mean only
in בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo. If it works to be an obligation
then I intend it to be binding in בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo.
If it doesn't then I don't intend it to be binding. Again,
you're probably not going through the math, you're just thinking in yourself,
you think בית חוניו Beis Chonyo works and you're thinking of it,
but we're going to interpret that what you're saying is I only
want this to be an obligation if I can satisfy it in
בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo. Okay so therefore by therefore at the end
of the day since you can't satisfy it in בית חוניו Beis
Chonyo you really don't have an obligation and in the case of
a נזיר Nazir you're really not a נזיר. Nazir. So when the
משנה Mishna says you're יוצא, Yotze, it doesn't really mean you're יוצא,
Yotze, it really means there's nothing to be יוצא Yotze because you
don't really have an obligation. Okay. So why then they don't bring
the
עולות Olos to the מקדש? Mikdash?
So where let's take a look. נזיר נמי, Nazir nami, by נזיר
Nazir also, האי גוונא לאיצטעורי נפשיה קמיכוין. hai gavna l'itztruye nasik kama
kavin. He's trying to afflict his soul, I mean he's trying to
be a נזיר, Nazir, אמר amar but he says, אי סגי בבית
חנא, isadye beBeis Chana, if it's going to work at בית חוניו,
Beis Chonyo, טרחנא, tarachna, I'll go to the effort and then I'll
be a נזיר. Nazir. טפי, Tfei, more than that, לא מצינא לאיצטעורי.
lo matzina l'itztruye. I will not want to afflict myself. Okay so
now what it really means is that the thing is not binding
at all. So there's two questions. First of all, how's that different
than רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? Right? That says that you're not a
נזיר, Nazir, it's not a vow, right? More or less the same
thing. And number two how do you deal with the first part
of it which is that it says if you do it in
the מקדש Mikdash you're יוצא? Yotze? So so that is presumably those
two answers themselves. Those two no well those two presumably answer themselves
and that's how it's different from רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon just said it's all or nothing. If it doesn't work
in בית חוניו Beis Chonyo it doesn't work at all. Here because
we're sort of interpreting it as I don't want to really schlep
to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, presumably what we're going to say
is that if you choose to schlep to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, then we're going to say at the bottom line is you
wanted to become a נזיר. Nazir. You wanted to bring a קרבן.
Korban. You were giving yourself an out that it you wouldn't have
to be bound to it if it forced you to go further
than the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But if you but if you
chose to go further than the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then we're
going to say then then you did then you did want it
to be binding so it's more like your choice. If you choose
to say I'm not going to bother then we'll say fine you
never wanted it to be binding if you don't want to bother.
If you choose to bring it then we'll say oh so it
seems like you were prepared to, so then it's going to be
חל. chal. So it's a very subtle difference between the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma and רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Both agree that the aspect
of בית חוניו Beis Chonyo is not חל chal at all and
if that's what you do then it was never a vow.
The difference
is as to whether do we recognize it as
a vow if you brought it if you go to ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Yes, probably.
That this will work for an עולה Olah but for a חטאת
Chatas you can't bring a חטאת Chatas unless you're obligated. So this
would seem to be Right it's only about an עולה, Olah, only
about free will sacrifice. Okay so this doesn't deal with... Right the
whole context here's been עולה. Olah. I'm sorry so what he's saying
is let's okay let's just finish the thought and then I'll get
to you. רב המנונא אמר לך. Rav Hununa amar lach. רב המנונא
Rav Hununa would say back, נזיר כי דקאמר. Nazir kideka amar. Look
you're right I have to interpret נזיר Nazir that way because נזיר
Nazir there's no way you can get out of it if you
by making some stipulation. The only way that you stop being a
נזיר Nazir is we say you know you never meant to be
a נזיר Nazir all together if you would not be able to
do it in בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo. So you're right about that.
But עולה, Olah,
so that's the phrase of the נזיר Nazir has to be read
when it says you're יוצא Yotze it has to be read as
you were never a נזיר Nazir because you only wanted it to
work in בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo. עולה, Olah, but the עולה Olah
case has more possibility and there I'll say we'll interpret it to
mean a greater demand. על מנת שלא אתחייב קאמר. Amanas d'lo echayiv
ka-amar. You really did sanctify it and you just meant that you're
not obligated. So again it's a little bizarre to take two statements
which are exactly parallel and interpret them differently but once again we
are choosing how to interpret what's not a question about trying to
have a whole discussion with you and figure out what you meant.
Okay so everybody agrees in the case of נזיר Nazir why we
have to allow the נזירות nezirus to end so we're going to
interpret it to mean that I only wanted to be a נזיר
Nazir if I could do it in בית חוניו. Beis Chonyo. And
if you're going to force tell me I can't I didn't want
to be a נזיר. Nazir. And when it says יוצא yotze it
doesn't really mean יוצא yotze it means you're not a נזיר. Nazir.
It's a way to kind of
get out of everything in what it seems to be.
Right. Okay. Again but if you chose to do it in the
מקדש Mikdash you were a נזיר Nazir so it sort of you
have that option. But in the case of an עולה Olah there
is there's... Debate. One says it's the same point, if I can't
bring it in בית חוניו, Beis Chonya, I'm not חייב chayav an
עולה Olah at all, it's not an עולה Olah at all. And
the other is no, no, by an עולה Olah what you really
meant is not it's all or nothing, you really meant I'm sanctifying
it regardless, but my obligation ends when I bring it in בית
חוניו. Beis Chonya. The difference is whether now that you're going to
bring it in בית חוניו, Beis Chonya, is it שחוטי חוץ? shchutei
chutz? Are you slaughtering a sacrifice outside of the מקדש? Mikdash? If
we say that you basically were it's all or nothing, if I
can't bring it in בית חוניו Beis Chonya I'm not חייב, chayav,
then that's... no, that's one read of the חכמים, Chachamim, then
then you're not slaughtering a sacrifice, right? You wanted to bring it
in בית חוניו Beis Chonya and if not it's nothing, so you're
not bringing a sacrifice. According to the other read, you sanctified it,
but but you just said my obligation ends once I bring it
in בית חוניו. Beis Chonya. So then you did actually slaughter a
sacrifice outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And that's what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say. So the only difference between the
the second read, רבא's Rava read and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon like
I said before, is if you choose to bring it in the
מקדש. Mikdash. That רבא Rava would say that you can choose and
then your vow is binding and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no,
once your vow was not binding in בית חוניו Beis Chonya it's
not binding at all. There's only a much more subtle difference.
Right,
it
just becomes a נדבה nedavah like any like... It could be if
you sanctified it, but there's certainly no... by the נזיר Nazir is
the bigger... but the נזיר Nazir is the bigger נפקא מינא. nafka
mina.
Yeah, but by me bringing it to the מקדש Mikdash doesn't
that make it a נדבה? nedavah? Maybe, maybe we would, but the
bigger difference would be felt in the case of the נזיר, Nazir,
that according to חכמים Chachamim you really were a נזיר Nazir and
according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you were nothing. So according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon if I actually went ahead and slaughtered in בית
חוניו Beis Chonya then it's not since it was never a קרבן
korban I'm not over anything?
No. And not even according to... and I can just eat it?
Yes. So and let's take a look. ואף רב יוחנן סבר להא
דרב המנונא, Ve'af Rav Yochanan savar le'ha de'Rav Hamnuna, and even רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan holds like רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, דאמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רב יוחנן, de'amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rav
Yochanan, הרי עלי עולה שאקריבנה בבית חוניו, Harey alai olah she'akrivena be'veis
chonyo, somebody says I will bring an עולה Olah in בית חוניו,
Beis Chonya, והקריבה בארץ ישראל, ve'hikriva be'eretz yisrael, and you brought it
not in בית חוניו, Beis Chonya, יצא ואינו בכרת, yatza ve'eyno be'kares,
you are יצא yatza and your punishment is כרת. kares. Why are
you יצא? yatza? You're יצא yatza because at the end of the
day we don't interpret בית חוניו Beis Chonya literally, we interpret בית
חוניו Beis Chonya to mean I won't be obligated to bring a
קרבן korban if something happens to this. That's how we're again we're
reinterpreting בית חוניו, Beis Chonya, that you limit your responsibility, but you're
חייב כרת chayav kares because at the end of the day you
actually did sanctify it. So this is the read that which works
better to create a bigger difference between the חכמים Chachamim and רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right, it doesn't work for נזיר, Nazir, but it
works like no, regardless I'm sanctifying it and בית חוניו Beis Chonya
just means I'm not liable for it. So then two things, number
one is once it's dead, no matter where it's you slaughtered it,
whether it was in בית חוניו Beis Chonya or anywhere else, any
in ישראל Israel doesn't matter, not the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you're
still your obligation ends. But because you did sanctify it, you're חייב
כרת chayav kares because it was a קרבן korban outside the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly,
הרי עלי עולה שאקריבנה במדבר, Harey alai olah she'akrivena be'midbar, I'm going
to bring it in the wilderness like not בית חוניו, Beis Chonya,
רש"י Rashi says you maybe thought like this wilderness was sanctified since
that's where the משכן Mishkan was, והקריבה בעבר הירדן, ve'hikriva be'ever hayarden,
he brought it even somewhere different than you sanctified, יצא, yatza, so
the first חידוש chiddush is you're יוצא, yotzei, your vow ends because
we don't interpret your vow in such a limited way of only
there, we mean that we interpret it through a lens of what's
a meaningful statement from the perspective of קרבנות. korbanot. Of קרבנות korbanot
that are brought in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that the meaningful
statement is I'm not obligated in liability if something happens to it.
That's how we interpret it, no longer בית חוניו, Beis Chonya, no
longer מדבר, midbar, we we don't acknowledge those institutions as having any
meaning. So if you're saying I'm going to do it there, what
you're really saying is I don't plan on being liable in in
substituting it if it gets brought outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. So
wherever it gets brought, your liability is
done in terms of having to bring a קרבן, korban, but ואינו
בכרת, ve'eyno be'kares, you get כרת kares because you slaughtered a קרבן
korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So basically we have three
possibilities in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is clear, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is you're trying to do it in בית חוניו
Beis Chonya you're trying to do so therefore and obviously you can't
do נזירות neziros or קרבן korban in בית חוניו Beis Chonya so
you did not take any vow, your vow is completely meaningless. Okay,
the חכמים Chachamim say no, you do have some form of a
vow but you're יצא. yatza. Now what does יצא yatza mean? So
there's two possibilities. One is reading it very close to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon which means that it's sort of if I wind up
bringing it outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and and you
told me that that wasn't good then I didn't really want to
obligate myself in anything. So therefore יצא yatza means if I did
it in בית חוניו Beis Chonya or I did it anywhere as
we see, my נזירות neziros never existed, my obligation never existed, so
יצא yatza doesn't mean יצא, yatza, יצא yatza actually means it never
existed. So how are they different than רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? They're
different because if I chose to do it in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash then ideal then I really do want my obligation to
be binding. So that would be the only difference, that if the
נזיר Nazir went to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash he really was
a נזיר. Nazir. Then you have רבא's Rava read, which is a
closer read to the משנה, Mishnah, not רבא, Rava, רב המנונא, Rav
Hamnuna, a closer read to the משנה, Mishnah, it doesn't work for
נזירות neziros but it's a better read for the קרבן korban case,
which is no, no, you took a vow, it really is binding
regardless. Okay, so what does בית חוניו Beis Chonya mean? And it
really is a sanctified animal. So what does בית חוניו Beis Chonya
mean? It's not like if it doesn't work in בית חוניו Beis
Chonya it's nothing, it is something. All בית חוניו Beis Chonya means
is the only meaning it has from a a הלכה halachic standpoint
is that if I bring it out of the that my obligation
ends once the animal dies even if it dies out of the
מקדש. Mikdash. So יצא yatza means your obligation ended because you had
made that stipulation. But because the animal is still sanctified, you're going
to be חייב כרת chayav kares if you brought it outside. And
now, so anyway, going back to the question of attitude towards בית
חוניו Beis Chonyo, *Beis Chonyo*, that possibility of חייב כרת *chayav kares*,
the משנה mishnah *mishnah* is a very soft יצא *yatza*, I mean,
using the phrase יצא *yatza* by בית חוניו Beis Chonyo, *Beis Chonyo*,
even if it means all of this, to frame it like that
really seems to give weight to בית חוניו Beis Chonyo *Beis Chonyo*,
and certainly what's missing is the עונש כרת *onesh kares*. So we're
going to have more of a critique coming up in the next
משנה mishnah *mishnah*. First Charlie and then you.
This second case would seem to be a case of ברירה *breira*
in a issue of a תורה Torah *Torah* law where they determine
whether the person is really a נזיר *nazir* by what he did
at the end of his נזירות *neziros*, which is...
Yeah, it's a good point. It's a very good point. Although again
here, you know, it's a whole question about choosing to interpret what
you mean rather than sort of... ברירה *breira* is more classically like
you say "I'm going to get to choose which thing I'm intending"
based on whatever. Here, you're right, there are some similarities, but again
here, especially because here we're going to interpret what you mean only
based on your actions at the end. It's a good point. I
mean the read that, you know, if I wind up doing it
then I really meant for it to be literal and if not
not, you know, that middle position is definitely... is definitely a hard
read. And I mean yeah, it's a subtle difference from ברירה *breira*
but the point is a good one. Yeah.
I didn't want to get into it now, but I was just
thinking, I was just wondering, you know, because if the משנה Mishna.
*mishnah* is something that we say was תורה מסיני *Torah MiSinai*, right?
Then you know, we're trying to recreate what was said. So how
much of the משנה Mishna *mishnah* is like, you know, מנחות *Menachos*?
It could be, you know, we just don't know who said it
and, you know, God talked מנחות *Menachos* in the תורה *Torah* and
mentioned תורה שבכתב *Torah SheBichesav* and mentioned תורה שבעל פה *Torah SheBe'al
Peh*, but I don't see God talking about like... I mean... בית
חוניו Beis Chonyo *Beis Chonyo* on הר סיני *Har Sinai*, which didn't...
חוניו Chonyo *Chonyo* didn't even exist until, you know, a thousand years
later. I don't exactly understand the question. No, my question is like
how much is the משנה *mishnah* trying to apply a תורה *Torah*
law to contemporary things versus trying to say like "this is what
actually...".
Both. משנה *mishnah* is not just a reformulated מדרש הלכה *midrash halacha*.
It's not just interpretation of the פסוקים *pesukim* reformulated. You have like
all of מסכת בבא בתרא *Masechet Bava Basra*, which has to do
with like no... almost no פסוקים *pesukim* at all, which is all
purely, you know, how the Rabbis, you know, deal with, you know,
apply things or invent rabbinic law and so on. So it's not
limited to interpretation of פסוקים *pesukim*. Right,
right, right,
yeah. Okay, let's take a look. Next משנה *mishnah*. Okay, we only
have... no, we'll have to talk more later. Next משנה *mishnah*. הכהנים
kohanim, ששימשו בבית חוניו Chonyo *Hakohanim sheshimshu Beis Chonyo*. Now, כהנים Kohanim
*kohanim* that actually worked, served in בית חוניו Beit Chonyo *Beis Chonyo*,
לא ישמשו במקדש שבירושלים *lo yeshamshu BeMikdash shebi'Yerushalayim*. Cannot now go and
work in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*.
They're permanently stigmatized. ואין צריך לומר לדבר אחר *Ve'ein tzarich lomar ledavar
acher*. And it goes without saying that somebody, a כהן kohen *kohen*
that worshipped עבודה זרה avoda zara, *avodah zarah* is completely excluded from
the worship in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. שנאמר she-ne'emar,
*Shene'emar*, as the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* says, אך לא יעלו *ach lo
ya'alu*... this is not about בית חוניו Chonyo *Beis Chonyo* but about
a similar phenomenon, אך לא יעלו כהני הבמות אל מזבח ה' בירושלים
*ach lo ya'alu kohanei habamos el mizbach Hashem bi'Yerushalayim*. The כהנים Kohanim,
*kohanim* that were on the במות *bamos* cannot go to the central
altar in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, כי אם אכלו מצות בתוך אחיהם *ki im
achlu matzos betoch acheihem*, but they can continue to eat the bread
with their brothers. What does that mean? הרי אלו כבעלי מומים *harei
elu k'ba'alei mumim*. They're like כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* that have blemishes. חולקין
ואוכלין *cholkin ve'ochlin*. They can have a portion of the sacrifices, ולא
מקריבין *velo makrivin*, but they cannot worship. So they're not completely excluded,
but they can still share, but in a way
this becomes a spiritual blemish. The fact that you served as a
כהן kohen *kohen* in this alternate מקדש Mikdash *mikdash*, similarly somebody who
served as a כהן kohen. *kohen* in a במה *bamah* when you're
supposed to worship in the central מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash*, a similar type
of an idea. It, you know, maybe has echoes of עבודה זרה
avoda zara *avodah zarah*, but the minimal problem is that it's outside
of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. You become invalidated. It's almost like a spiritual מום
*mum*, a religious blemish, but you are still allowed to eat in
the קרבנות korbanos. *korbanos*. So let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. אמר רב יהודה כהן kohen ששחט לעבודת כוכבים קרבנו ריח
ניחוח korbano reiach nichoach, *Amar Rav Yehuda kohen sheshachat l'avodas kochavim korbano
reiach nichoach*. If a כהן kohen *kohen* slaughters for עבודה זרה avoda
zara, *avodah zarah*, and then presumably רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says he did
תשובה teshuvah. *teshuvah*, which is not stated here, but then, not the
קרבן korban *korban* to the עבודה זרה avoda zara, *avodah zarah* is
ריח ניחוח *reiach nichoach*. Now he worships in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash? *Beis HaMikdash*. That would be an accepted sacrifice. So the fact
that he slaughtered to עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah* does not
invalidate him. What do you do about the משנה *mishnah*?
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*?
No, not in the case.
We're not giving out מיתה *misah*. That's not our issue. Okay, אמר
רב יצחק בר אבדימי מאי קרא *Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi mai
kra*? Where do you see this from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? יען
אשר ישרתו אותם לפני גלוליהם *ya'an asher yeshartu osam lifnei giluleihem* because
they served in front of their, you know, abominations, idols, והיו לבית
ישראל למכשול עון *vehayu l'veis Yisrael l'michshol avon* and they were for
the children of Israel for a stumbling and a sin. על כן
נשאתי ידי עליהם נאם ה' *al kein nasasi yadi aleihem ne'um Hashem*.
I've lifted up my hand about them, I've taken a vow says
God. ונשאו עונם *venas'u avonam* and they shall carry their sins. So
this is about the priests that served for עבודה זרה avoda zara,
*avodah zarah*. וכתיב *Uchesiv* after it says, ולא יגשו אלי לכהן לי
*velo yigshu elai lechahen li*. And they cannot come to serve me
anymore. So a כהן kohein *kohen* that worshipped עבודה זרה avoda zara?
*avodah zarah* cannot serve in the מקדש Mikdash. *mikdash*. So how does
this allow for the case of slaughtering? So he says, ah, but
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says אי עביד שירות sheirus *ei avid sheirus*.
It says אשר ישרתו *asher yeshartu*, that they actually served, they did
a type of a שירות sheirus *sheirus*, a priestly service. So if
they did a priestly service in, then they become invalidated. שחיטה shechita,
לאו שירות sheirus, הוא *Shechitah lav sheirus hu*. Slaughtering is not a
priestly service because remember, a non-כהן kohein, *kohen* can be a שוחט
*shochet*. So yes, you did a terrible sin, but here's conceptually, it's
not something that besmirches your כהונה kehuna *kehunah*. You did a terrible
sin. There's lots of people that's done terrible sins. You do תשובה
teshuvah. *teshuvah*, we move on. But the sense is has your כהונה
kehuna. *kehunah* become besmirched? If it was a type of a bringing
of a קרבן korban, *korban* that a non-כהן kohein, *kohen* can do,
it's not identified in terms of your כהונה kehuna *kehunah*. you have
somehow violated your כהונה kehuna, in a way that's irreparable.
So that's just this ענין. inyan. So what you're seeing is that
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim was not שחיטה, shchita it's everything else. Yes.
And then רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's case of שחט, shachat, since it's
not really considered an עבודה avoda then therefore I can do it.
Correct.
איתמר, Itmar, so we taught. שוגג בזריקה. Shogeg bizrika. Now that's the
case about you were מזיד בשחיטה meizid beshchita and we're saying that
that's not שברא. shavra. Let's talk about another perhaps unambiguous case. You
did זריקה zrika of a קרבן korban to עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
also pretty serious, but the one thing that made it not the
most serious is you were שוגג. shogeg. You didn't realize it was
עבודה זרה avoda zara, or something. You thought it was in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? or you thought it was מותר muttar to
worship עבודה זרה, avoda zara. I don't know what your שוגג shogeg
is. Okay? So how much does that save, sort of free you
from this stigma and allow you to now work in the בית
המקדש? Beis HaMikdash Okay, רב נחמן אמר קרבנו ריח ניחוח, Rav Nachman
amar korbano reiach nichoach, afterwards your קרבן, korban. not the one that
you gave to the עבודה זרה, avoda zara, your new קרבן korban.
now will be accepted by God. רב ששת אמר אין קרבנו ריח
ניחוח, Rav Sheshess amar ein korbano reiach nichoach. it won't be accepted
by God. אמר רב ששת מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rav Sheshess mana
amina lah, where would I know this? דכתיב, Dechisiv, ויהיו לבית ישראל
למכשול עון, veyihyu levais Yisrael lemichshol avon, for a stumbling sin. מאי
לאו, Mai lav, so we read that word a stumbling, או מכשול
o michshol either stumbling או עון o avon or a sin. ומכשול,
Umichshol, to stumble, is שוגג shogeg ועון veavon and a sin is
willful is מזיד. meizid. So even if it's a שוגג, shogeg, that
doesn't matter, you are still stigmatized and besmirched. רב נחמן אמר, Rav
Nachman amar no, מכשול דעון, michshol deavon, the stumbling of a willful
sin, but it's only if it's willful. אמר רב נחמן מנא אמינא
לה, Amar Rav Nachman mana amina lah, how do I know that
only if it's willful? דתניא Detanya in the ברייתא, braisa, והקריב הכהן
על הנפש השגגת בחטא בשגגה. vehikriv hakohen al hanefesh hashogeges bechet bishgaga.
So this is about bringing a sacrifice, we had this recently in
the פרשה, parsha, about for people that worship for the sin of
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And we say, so it's the כהן kohein
will bring for the soul that sins when it sins by in
error. מלמד שהכהן מתכפר ידי עצמו. Melamed shehakohen miskapair yedei atzmo. So
we're reading it על הנפש השוגגת, al hanefesh hashogeges, even his own
soul. So if a כהן kohein. was a שוגג shogeg in עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah he can bring his own קרבן. korban. Okay? So
here you see שוגג דעבודה זרה shogeg deavoda zara and he's bringing
his own קרבן. korban So you see, doing עבודה זרה בשוגג avoda
zara bishogeg does not invalidate him from doing the עבודה. avoda. במאי,
Bemai, how did he do how did he do עבודה זרה? avodah
zarah. אילימא בשחיטה, Ilima beshchita, if it was בשחיטה, beshchita, מאי איריא
שוגג? mai irya shogeg? אפילו מזיד נמי. Afilu meizid nami. So why
would the תורה have to tell us that he's not invalidated because
he was a שוגג? shogeg? We just taught before that by שחיטה
shchita. even if he was willful, he's not invalidated to be a
כהן. kohein. אלא לאו, Ela lav, if it's telling us something new,
it must be telling us בזריקה, bizrika, that it was a case
of actually the sprinkling of the blood, but because he was a
שוגג, shogeg, it does not invalidate him. So that's what he's learning
from that פסוק. ורב ששת, VeRav Sheshess, and רב ששת Rav Sheshess
who says he is invalidated, אמר לך, amar lach, he'll say to
you, לעולם בשחיטה ובמזיד. Leolam beshchita ube'meizid. It really is talking about
שחיטה. shchita ובמזיד לא נעשה משרת לעבודת כוכבים. Ube'meizid lo na'aseh mesharais
la'avodas kochavim. But רב ששת Rav Sheshess is going to say to
you, again רב ששת Rav Sheshess is consistently the more lenient one,
and he is going to say no it's talking about
שחיטה shchita's and he is going to say no I'm sorry רב
ששת Rav Sheshess is consistently the more strict one. I say no,
if the שחיטה's shchita's done במזיד, be'meizid, it does label him. And
the only one that gets off is שחיטה בשוגג. shchita bishogeg. So
רב ששת Rav Sheshess basically here's how it works. Everybody agrees שחיטה's
shchita less severe than the other things. רב ששת Rav Sheshess says
that שחיטה shchita even במזיד be'meizid the כהן kohein. is not invalidated,
זריקה zrika he's only invalidated במזיד. be'meizid. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman
makes it bigger. שחיטה shchita's you're only not invalidated if you were
שוגג, shogeg, and זריקה zrika you're invalidated in all cases even if
you're שוגג. shogeg. Okay? So רב ששת Rav Sheshess is consistent... I'm
sorry, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman
is consistently more lenient, more more accepting after the fact than רב
ששת. Rav Sheshess. Now the reason here is, he says נעשה משרת
לעבודת כוכבים. na'aseh mesharais la'avodas kochavim. Not because you became
a servant to idolatry. So what that presumably means
is, could be understood as he's saying look, I understand your idea
that it's not directly sort of desecrate the קדושה kedusha of the
כהונה kehuna, because the שחיטה's shchita not an act of כהונה. kehuna.
But that doesn't matter. If you were willful, a willful worshipper of
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah that identifies you as a worshipper of עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, and that is what invalidates you. It's not that
you defiled your כהונה kehuna directly because שחיטה shchita. wasn't an act
of כהונה, kehuna but nevertheless by being a person that has served
an idol, you can't be a כהן kohein as if you did
it willfully, even שחיטה.
shchita Okay, שחיטה shchita is it not one of the עבודות avodos
like we see השתחויה hishtachavaya and all that?
So it is. It is for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah So that
also could be what he means. That even if it's not an
עבודה avoda for כהונה, kehunah. it's an עבודה avoda for... but it's
an עבודה avoda for כהונה. kehunah, Okay, ואזדו לטעמייהו, ve'azdu leta'amayhu, they
go according to their reasoning. דאיתמר, De'itmar, it was said: מזיד בשחיטה,
meizid beshchita, if you were מזיד בשחיטה, meizid beshchita, רב נחמן אמר
קרבנו ריח ניחוח, Rav Nachman amar korbano reiach nichoach. it's still okay.
שחיטה shechitah. is out of the category. רב ששת אמר אין קרבנו
ריח ניחוח. Rav Sheshess amar ein korbano reiach nichoach, No, you no
longer can bring a קרבן. רב נחמן אמר קרבנו ריח ניחוח דלא
עבד שירות, Rav Nachman amar korbano reiach nichoach dela avad sheirus, because
you did not actually do an act of כהונה kehunah. service, although
as Michael said correctly it was an act of עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah. but it's not כהונה kehunah service. רב ששת אמר אין קרבנו
ריח ניחוח, Rav Sheshet amar ein korbano reiach nichoach. it is not
no longer accepted, נעשה משרת לעבודת כוכבים, na'aseh mesharais la'avodas kochavim,
you have become nevertheless a servant to the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah
Okay, אמר רב נחמן מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rav Nachman mana amina
lah, how do I know? Now we're now we're going to discuss.
The מזיד meizid in the שחיטה. shechitah How do I know this?
That even מזיד meizid in the שחיטה shechitah, is כשר kasher in
the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. דתניא: detanya: כהן שעבד עבודת כוכבים בשוגג.
kohein she'avad avodas kochavim b'shogeg. A כהן kohein did עבודה זרה avodah
zarah. and he did תשובה. teshuvah? So here is the תשובה. teshuvah.
קרבנו ריח ניחוח. korbano reiach nichoach. So his קרבן is now accepted.
במאי, bemai, what are we talking about? אילימא בשוגג, eileima b'shogeg, if
he did it unintentionally, מאי ושב? mai v'shav? Why do you need
to say he did
תשובה? teshuvah, ושב ועומד הוא. v'shav v'omed hu. He already is in
a state of doing תשובה. teshuvah Meaning, obviously even sins בשוגג b'shogeg
need תשובה, teshuvah? but in terms of the question of being able
to be accepted as a כהן, Kohen since you were not willful,
that act never invalidated you. אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, so if you
need to do תשובה teshuvah, to become re-accepted as a כהן, kohen
אלא פשיטא במזיד, ela peshita b'meizid, it must be you did it
willfully. ואי בזריקה, v'ei b'zrikah, and if we're talking about זריקה, zrikah,
כי שב מאי הוה? ki shav mai hava? Who cares that you
did תשובה? teshuvah If you were willful and you did זריקה, zrikah,
you're completely excluded. הא עבד ליה שירות. ha avad lei sheirus. You
actually used your service of a כהן kohen to עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah? אלא לאו בשחיטה. ela lav b'shchitah. It must be בשחיטה. b'shchitah.
So basically what he says is a שוגג shogeg was never invalidated.
Who is the only person that can be invalidated and reclaim it?
Somebody who did שחיטה במזיד. shchitah b'meizid. As long as you didn't
do תשובה, teshuvah, we won't re-accept you, but after you've done תשובה
teshuvah we will re-accept you. And that shows that even מזיד meizid
on שחיטה, shchitah. as long as it's בשחיטה, b'shchitah, you can be
re-accepted. That's what he says. רב ששת אמר לך, Rav Sheshet amar
lach, רב ששת Rav Sheshet would say, לעולם בשוגג. le'olam b'shogeg. No,
we are talking about שוגג shogeg by שחיטה. shchitah So why does
it say ושב? v'shav? והכי קאמר: v'hachi ka'amar: אם שב מעיקרו, im
shav me'ikaro, if you were always in a state of תשובה, teshuvah,
which means you were never willful, דכי עביד, d'ki avid, that when
you did it, בשוגג עביד, b'shogeg avid, you did it בשוגג, b'shogeg,
קרבנו ריח ניחוח. korbano reiach nichoach. Then you did not become invalidated
if you did the שחיטה בשוגג. shchitah b'shogeg. ואי לאו אין קרבנו
ריח ניחוח. v'ei lav ein korbano reiach nichoach. It is no longer
accepted. So there we have two debates. Everybody agrees שחיטה shchitah is
less
severe. רב ששת Rav Sheshet is more strict. רב ששת Rav Sheshet
says מזיד meizid with שחיטה shchitah will always exclude you. By the
other thing, even שוגג shogeg will exclude you. And רב נחמן Rav
Nachman is much more accepting. רב נחמן Rav Nachman is after the
fact and he'll say that שחיטה shchitah, never invalidates you as long
as you did תשובה teshuvah afterwards, and even זריקה zrikah doesn't invalidate
you if you were שוגג. shogeg. Now we deal with other forms
of worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah that are not necessarily an act
of שירות of
כהונה. kehunah השתחוה לעבודת כוכבים, hishtachavah l'avodas kochavim, let's say you bowed
down to idols. רב נחמן אמר קרבנו ריח ניחוח. Rav Nachman amar
korbano reiach nichoach. Again, רב נחמן Rav Nachman is much more accepting.
Nevertheless, it wasn't an act of שירות of כהונה, kehunah, so even
though personally you were an עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, it
does not defile your כהונה. kehunah. And now assuming you did תשובה,
teshuvah you can go back and bring קרבנות. רב ששת אמר Rav
Sheshess amar אין קרבנו ריח ניחוח. ein korbano reiach nichoach, No, sorry,
the same way he said by שחיטה, shechitah if you did a
serious act of עבודה avodah זרה, that defines your identity even if
it was not using your כהונה kehunah role to do it. הודה
לעבודת כוכבים, hodah l'avodas kochavim, let's say you didn't even do an
act of worship, you just accepted an idol as your god. So
again, רב נחמן אמר Rav Nachman amar, קרבנו ריח ניחוח. רב נחמן
Rav Nachman as we know says okay, you've done תשובה teshuvah now,
you can bring it. רב ששת אמר לך Rav Sheshet amar lach
no, אין קרבנו ריח ניחוח. ein korbano reiach nichoach. Once you're an
עובד עבודה זרה במזיד, oved avodah zarah b'meizid, even if it was
not through a כהונה kehunah, act, you can no longer be a
כהן. וצריכא, v'tzricha, and you need that to all the cases. דאי
אשמעינן הך קמייתא, d'ei ashmi'inan hach kamaisa, the earlier case about שחיטה
shchitah and about זריקה בשוגג, zrikah b'shogeg, בהיא קאמר רב
ששת משום דעבד ליה שירות. behi ka'amar Rav Sheshet mishum d'avad lei
sheirus.
There רב ששת Rav Sheshet would be strict because at least you
did שירות, you did זריקה. zrikah. So he's strict even though it's
שוגג. shogeg. אבל שחיטה דלא עבד ליה שירות, aval shchitah d'la avad
lei sheirus, שחיטה shchitah, which is not an act of כהונה, kehuna.
אימא מודה ליה eima modeh lei maybe he'd go easier on him
to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So he had to tell us no
that even by שחיטה, shchitah, if it's במזיד, b'meizid, he's not going
easy. ואי אשמעינן שחיטה, v'ei ashmi'inan shchitah, had it just
said שחיטה, משום דעבד ליה עבודה. mishum d'avad lei avodah. At least
it's still an עבודה avodah that is done in the מקדש Mikdash,
even though it's not an עבודה avodah of כהונה. אבל השתחוה דלא
עביד ליה עבודה, aval hishtachavah d'la avid lei avodah, but bowing down,
which is an עבודה avodah for עבודה avodah זרה but it's not
an עבודה of the עבודות avodos in the מקדש, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe he would agree to רב נחמן Rav Nachman that that
does not invalidate. וצריכא. v'tzricha. ואי אשמעינן השתחוה, v'ei ashmi'inan hishtachavah, if
it said bowing down, משום דעבד ליה מעשה, mishum d'avad lei maaseh,
at least it's an act of עבודה זרה. אבל הודאה דדיבורא בעלמא,
aval hoda'ah d'dibbura b'alma, but just an acceptance of עבודה זרה which
is just verbal, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe he would not invalidate
the כהן. וצריכא. v'tzricha. So רב ששת Rav Sheshet is very strict.
Any person that is a willful עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah
can never again serve as a כהן. רב נחמן Rav Nachman is
much more tolerant; he says it's only the narrowly defined misuse of
your כהונה which invalidates you. Now we are really running out of
time, but I did want to just say importantly there is a
discussion in this
תוספות Tosafos that discusses the question about a כהן that apostatizes
and then comes back. Can he do נשיאת כפיים? nesias kapayim? So
he quotes a book called ספר הזהיר, Sefer HaZahir, which some people
misquote as הזהר, haZohar, but תוספות Tosafos was not quoting the זוהר.
Zohar. Anyway, it's actually a גאוניק Geonic work called והזהיר, V'Hizhir, which
actually says that a כהן should not do נשיאת כפיים nesias kapayim
if he became an apostate and came back based on an analogy
to these types of things. And רש"י Rashi in a תשובה says
no, absolutely he can. First of all he says the גמרא Gemara
in the משנה says that he's considered like a בעל מום. baal
mum. Now it's true the משנה is talking about בית חוניו, Chonyo
which wasn't a בית עבודה זרה, beis avodah zarah, but רש"י chooses
to say that worst case scenario even when it's real. or apostasy,
he's at worst a בעל מום Baal Mum and a בעל מום
Baal Mum can be נושא כפיים. Nosei Kapayim. רש״י Rashi also says,
you know, that the גמרא only excludes it from work in the
מקדש. What we do about ברכת כהנים, Birkas Kohanim, you know, is
outside of the מקדש, and also included in this is not just
the question about being נושא כפיים Nosei Kapayim but it's also about
getting like the first עליה aliyah and so on. There's a similar
תוספות Tosafot that discusses the question, this question in סוטה Sotah about
a case of a כהן that killed somebody, you know, there's a
whole discussion about can he be נושא כפיים. Nosei Kapayim. What's there
said explicitly, but it was implicit here, is also the sort of
תקנת השבים. takanas hashavim. That to what degree if the person even
if he does תשובה is not going to be able to regain
their status, so how much are you sort of pushing people away,
rather than bringing them close, and how much that factors in. So
there's a lot of interesting discussion around this about applying it to
like contemporary realities. Now... Rabbi Saperstein?
Well, that's the question. We can, I mean I don't know, can
people, I don't know who's running to daven, I mean if people
can give ten more minutes?
I already davened.
I can do ten minutes. I can do ten minutes. All right,
so all right, so let I'm just going to try to get
us closer to the bottom. All right. ואין צריך לומר דבר אחר.
Ve’ein tzarich lomar davar acher. So certainly so that's if he served
in בית חוניו, Chonyo. it goes without saying if he served in
a בית עבודה זרה. Beis Avodah Zarah.
Actually a lot of our discussion had been בית עבודה זרה, Beis
Avodah Zarah, but now we're turning to that part of the משנה.
ודקאמר אין צריך לומר דבר אחר, Vedeka’amar ein tzarich lomar davar acher,
since you say that it goes without saying something else, מכלל דבית
חוניו לאו עבודה זרה היא. michlal deBeis Chonyo lav avodah zarah hi.
So you're saying the implicit point in the משנה is that בית
חוניו Chonyo, is not a בית עבודה זרה. Beis Avodah Zarah. תניא
כמאן דאמר בית חוניו לאו עבודה זרה היא. Tanya keman de’amar Beis
Chonyo lav avodah zarah hi. So this so we taught in a
ברייתא Braisa similarly like the opinion that says that בית חוניו Chonyo
is not a house of עבודה זרה. דתניא, Detanya, we taught a
ברייתא, Braisa, אותה שנה שמת שמעון הצדיק. osah shanah shemeis Shimon HaTzaddik.
So the year that שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzaddik died, אמר להם, amar
lahem, so when he came out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
on יום כיפור, he said to the people around him, which were
his friends, שנה זו הוא מת, shanah zu hu meis, this year
he will die, he meaning himself, he knew he was going to
die that year. So אמרו לו מנין אתה יודע, amru lo minayin
atah yodeia, how do you know? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said
to them, כל יום הכיפורים נזדמן לי זקן אחד לבוש לבנים ונתעטף
לבנים. kol yom hakippurim nizdamen li zaken echad levush levanim venisatef levanim.
Every time that I go into the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, I
see somebody in the visage of an old man wearing white clothing,
wrapped in white, ונכנס עמי, venichnas immi, he comes with me into
the בית קדש הקדשים, Beis Kodesh HaKodashim, ויצא עמי, veyatza immi, and
he goes out with me. So presumably that was, you know, God's
presence. שנה זו, Shanah zu, this year, נזדמן לי זקן אחד לבוש
שחורים ונתעטף שחורים. nizdamen li zaken echad levush shechorim venisatef shechorim. I
saw this older, this elderly man dressed in black and wrapped in
black, ונכנס עמי, venichnas immi, he went with me into the קדשי
קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, ולא יצא עמי, velo yatza immi, and he didn't
come out with me, which somehow is you're going to leave and
not come back, and a sign of mourning. So he knew he
was going to die. לאחר הרגל חלה שבעה ימים ומת, Le’achar haregel
chalah shivah yamim umeis, after the festival he lived through סוכות, Succos,
he was sick for seven days and he died. ונמנעו אחיו הכהנים
לברך בשם. Venimnu echav hakohanim levarech baShem. And his fellow כהנים after
him no longer did ברכת כהנים Birkas Kohanim with God's explicit name,
the שם המפורש, Shem HaMeforash, because, you know, that was something that
required a serious level of piety to say that name and to
say it in a way that would not bring injury. So therefore
after him they no longer used the explicit name of God. בשעת
פטירתו, Besha’as petirato, now when he was dying, אמר להם, amar lahem,
he said to them, חוניו בני ישמש תחתי, Chonyo beni yeshamesh tachtai,
חוניו Chonyo my son should serve under me as a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. נתקנא בו שמעי אחיו, Nitkana bo Shimei achiv, שמעי Shimei
his brother was jealous of him, שהיה גדול ממנו שתי שנים ומחצה,
shehayah gadol mimenu shtei shanim vachetzi, that שמעי Shimei was the older
brother by two and a half years, and he was jealous that
חוניו Chonyo, had been picked to be the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
אמר לו, Amar lo, so he said to his younger brother חוניו
Chonyo who had been tapped, בוא ואלמדך סדר עבודה, bo ve’alameidcha seder
avodah, let me go show you how the עבודה gets done. הלבישו
באונקלי, Hilbisho be’unkali, he made him, he dressed him in some type
of a cloak which as we'll see later in the story is
a female garb, וחגרו בצלצול, vechagaro betzilzul, and he, sort of, you
know, girded him with a belt but that also refers to like
a women's belt. והעמידו אצל המזבח, Vehe’emido etzel hamizbeiach, and he stood
him by the altar. And then he got him all ready to
say this is how you inaugurate כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gedolim. תוספות Tosafot
says, I don't get it, if חוניו Chonyo. was chosen, how could
he be duped and think that this is what happened? So תוספות
Tosafot says two answers. One is he was chosen for his piety,
not necessarily that he actually had been familiar with how a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol works, but he was the more pious one. The
other explanation is תוספות Tosafot still not satisfied. He says I still
don't get it, he never in his life saw a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol serve? His father was a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. He
says well, maybe he didn't know how a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
was inaugurated. He thought that this was something special of how they're
inaugurated. Right? For his whole life. Okay. אמר להם לאחיו הכהנים, Amar
lahem le’echav hakohanim, so now the older brother שמעי Shimei said to
his fellow כהנים, ראו מה נדר זה וקיים לאהובתו, re’u mah nadar
zeh vekiyyem le’ahuvato, see what this person, my brother, vowed and fulfilled
to his beloved one, his wife. אותו היום שאשמש בכהונה גדולה, Oto
hayom she’eshamesh bikehunah gedolah, here's what he said to his wife: that
day that I become a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, אלבוש באונקלי שלך,
elbash be’unkali shelach, I'll wear your robe, ואחגור בצלצול שלך, ve’achgor betzilzul
shelach, I'll gird myself in your belt. So basically he said not
only is the guy an ignoramus, or maybe he's not an ignoramus,
but look how he is like, you know, sort of degrading the
כהונה, making a mockery of it. בקשו אחיו הכהנים להרגו. Bikshu echav
hakohanim lehargo.
So his fellow כהנים wanted
to kill Shimei, they thought he was completely disrespectful. the office. I'm
sorry, חוניו. Chonyo So רץ מפניהם, ratz mifnehem, they ran... he ran
away from them, ורצו אחריו, varatzu acharav, they ran after him. הלך
לאלכסנדריא של מצרים, halach l'Alexandri shel Mitzrayim, and he came to Alexandria
of Egypt where he maybe got refuge. ובנה שם מזבח והעלה עליו
לשם עבודת כוכבים, u-vanah sham mizbeach ve-he-elah alav le-shem avodat kochavim, and
he built an altar and he built it for idolatry. So even
if though, you know, according
to one of the תוספות, Tosafos, he was chosen for his piety,
but basically, you know, this is a sort of an understandable psychological
reaction. You're feeling completely rejected and mocked and tricked, and it's like
to heck with all of this and you're totally rejecting it and
doing the opposite. And he became and he made this for idolatry.
וכששמעו חכמים בדבר, u-che-she-sham'u chachamim badavar, when the rabbis heard this, אמרו,
amru, מה זה שלא ירד לכך, mah zeh she-lo yarad le-kach, what
is the person that did not go down to this, meaning did
not become a position of greatness, היורד לה על אחת כמה וכמה,
ha-yored lah al achat kamah ve-chamah, one who accepts a position of
greatness how much more so. What does this mean? So what this
means is, it's the... the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom had a good
explanation. Let me just re-read it. He says, one minute. Yeah, it's
not talking about חוניו, Chonyo, it's talking about שמעי. Shimi. That he
was never... he never had been a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, and
he was so jealous of this office that look to what... look
what he did and look what it led. How much more so
somebody that actually has a position of authority, how much more will
they jealously protect it and, you know, and what it can lead
to. So basically that this was like an object lesson about, you
know, about what the... the... you know, sort of like, well not
just how power corrupts, but the desire for office and the desire
for status, how it can lead to terrible things. Okay, so that
was one version. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says. אמר לו רבי יהודה, amar lo Rabbi Yehuda,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said no, לא כך היה מעשה, lo kach
hayah ma'aseh, that wasn't what happened. אלא לא קיבל עליו חוניו, ela
lo kibel alav Chonyo, חוניו chose not to be. He was picked,
he was tapped, but he said I'm not going to do it.
שהיה שמעי אחיו גדול ממנו שש שנים ומחצה, she-hayah Shimi achiv gadol
mimenu shesh shanim u-mechetza, I have an older brother, שמעי Shimi is
two and a half years older, let him be the כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. ואף על פי כן, ve-af al pi chen, and even
though he was trying to be a צדיק, tzadik, נתקנא בו חוניו
בשמעי אחיו. nitkana bo Chonyo bi-Shimi achiv. In the end, שמעי Shimi
became... was the כהן גדול kohen gadol and חוניו was jealous. Like
he did the right thing, but it didn't stop the fact that
he was still jealous that here he was tapped and שמעי Shimi
was the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, even though it was his... he
said, you know, he made it happen. אמר לו, amar lo, so
he, חוניו, tried to do in his older brother. So אמר לו,
amar lo, he said to שמעי, Shimi, בוא ואלמדך סדר עבודה. bo
ve-almedcha seder avodah. So he said to שמעי, Shimi, he said the
same story but reversed. He said to שמעי, Shimi, let me show
you how you get inaugurated. Okay. והלבישו באונקלי וחגרו בצלצול, ve-hilbisho be-unkli
ve-chagaro be-tziltzul, put him in this cloak and this belt, והעמידו אצל
המזבח, ve-he-emido etzel hamizbeach, put him by the altar. אמר להם לאחיו
הכהנים, amar lahem le-echav hakohanim, he said to his brothers הכהנים, kohanim
ראו מה נדר זה וקיים לאהבתו. re'u mah nadar zeh ve-kiyam le-ahavato.
See what this one, you know, my older brother שמעי, Shimi, vowed
and fulfilled to his wife. אותו היום שאשתמש בכהונה גדולה אלבוש באונקלי
שלך ואחגור בצלצול שלך. oto hayom she-eshtamesh bi-chuna gedola elbash be-unkli shelach
ve-achgor be-tziltzul shelach. That day that I use as a כהן גדול
kohen gadol I'll wear your dress and I'll put on your belt.
ביקשו אחיו הכהנים להורגו. bikshu echav hakohanim le-horgo. So now the other
הכהנים wanted to kill שמעי Shimi because they saw שמעי Shimi was
the one that was disparaging the כהונה. סח להם כל המאורע. sach
lahem kol hamora. So שמעי Shimi said no, wait, I've been duped,
it was my brother חוניו that made me do all of this.
So ביקשו להרוג את חוניו. bikshu le-harog et Chonyo. Somehow he was
very articulate and he managed to turn the tide, right, and they
now they all wanted to kill חוניו. רץ מפניהם, ratz mifnehem, so
now חוניו was running away. ורצו אחריו ורץ לבית המלך. ve-ratzu acharav
ve-ratz le-veit hamelech. He went to the king's house. ורצו אחריו, ve-ratzu
acharav, and they ran after him. כל הרואה אותו אומר זהו זהו.
kol haro'eh oto omer zehu zehu. Everybody who saw him said he's
the one, he's the one, go get him. It's an interesting, like,
the additional color here, like how did reversing the story lead to
running to the king's house and everybody pointing him out? I don't
know. הלך לאלכסנדריא של מצרים, halach l'Alexandri shel Mitzrayim, he finally got
to Alexandria of Egypt. ובנה שם מזבח והעלה עליו לשם שמים. u-vanah
sham mizbeach ve-he-elah alav le-shem shamayim. And he used it for a
house for God. שנאמר, ביום ההוא יהיה מזבח לה' בתוך ארץ מצרים.
ba-yom ha-hu yihyeh mizbeach l'Adonai be-toch eretz Mitzrayim. There'll be an altar
for God in the land of Egypt. ומצבה אצל גבולה לה'. u-matzeva
etzel gevulah l'Adonai. And a pillar by its border to God. וכששמעו
חכמים, u-che-she-sham'u chachamim, now apparently the reason this version has it being
לשם שמים le-shem shamayim is because even though in the end, you
know, he was nasty and he tried to do in his brother,
but I would say two things: number one is he started off
with, you know, pure intentions, doing the right thing, so his jealousy
got the better of him, but ultimately he was like somebody who
wanted to do the right thing, so I think that's framing it.
And also because in the end he was being pursued for his
own deviousness, he was not being like rejected, you know, from being
a כהן and made a mockery of, in terms of you were
trying to be a כהן and you were made a mockery of,
so it doesn't lead to the same type of, I think, you
know, angry rejection of the whole system, right? It was his own
deviousness that did him in. So therefore, okay, he's setting up his
own authority, but it's still going to be לשם שמים, le-shem shamayim,
just be his own בית המקדש. וכששמעו חכמים בדבר, u-che-she-sham'u chachamim badavar,
when the rabbis heard about this, אמרו, amru, ומה זה שברח ממנה
כך, u-mah zeh she-barach mimena kach, somebody who was running away from,
you know, power and authority and status, you know, nevertheless was so
jealous that it led him to try to capture through this whole
thing, although he initially tried to disavow it, המבקש לירד לה, ha-mevakesh
le-yerad lah, somebody who is actually pursuing... Pursuing status and power על
אחת כמה וכמה, al achat kama v'khama, how much more so are
they going to do wrong things in order to achieve power. So
however you learn it it was a lesson about the desire for
power and what it can lead to. Let's just read like two
more sentences to wrap this up. תניא אמר רבי יהושע בן פרחיה:
Tanya Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Perachia: בתחילה כל אומר עלי לה—originally betchila
kol omer ali la if anybody would have told me go up
to it, it's interesting as opposed to before they were talking ירד
yarad to go down but it's talking about the same thing, take
a position of authority—אני כופתו ונותנו לפני אריה. ani kofso u'notno lifnei
aryeh. I would have bound him and put him before a lion.
He wanted to avoid positions of power and authority; he saw it
as dangerous and evil. עתה נא, ata na, because he eventually actually
became a נשיא nasi and he had a position, so now that
I've been
put in the position now I jealously protect it. כל האומר לי
לירד ממנה, kol ha'omer li lered mimena, if
anybody tells me to step down from this אני מטיל עליו קומקום
של חמים, ani matil alav kumkum shel chamim, I will throw on
him a flask filled with hot water. Now it's not as bad,
I'm not going to put him before a lion, but anyway what
he says is you see what happens; you could want to not
have the power but once you're in the office then you become
jealous to protect it. Okay שהרי שאול sheharei Shaul and I'll tell
you where you see this: ברח ממנה, barach mimena, שאול Shaul first
didn't want to be king, actually just this week's הפטרה. haftarah. שעלה
she'ala and once he got a position of power ביקש להרוג את
דוד, bikesh laharog et David, he tried to kill דוד David in
order to protect it so you can see what power and authority
and status does to a person. Okay one last statement. אמר ליה
מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לאביי: amar lei Mar kashisha brei d'Rav
Chisda l'Abaye: רב מאיר האי קרא דרבי יהודה מאי עביד ליה? Rav
Meir hai kra d'Rabbi Yehuda mai avid lei? What does רב מאיר
Rav Meir do with this פסוק that says there will be a
house of God in Egypt if he says it was a house
of עבודה זרה? כדתניא k'detanya like we taught in the ברייתא Baraita
לאחר מפלתו של סנחריב l'achar mapalato shel Sancheiriv after סנחריב Sancheiriv was
defeated יצא חזקיה ומצא בני מלכים כיושבים בקרונות של זהב, yatza Chizkiya
umatzah b'nei melachim k'yoshvim b'karonot shel zahav, he found these princes that
were in golden wagons. Apparently I don't know what the golden wagon
is about but anyway apparently after סנחריב Sancheiriv and his army had
been destroyed חזקיה Chizkiya felt it was a good opportunity to spread
belief of God throughout the world so he went to these various
princes and he made them vow not to worship עבודה זרה שנאמר
ביום ההוא יהיו חמש ערים בארץ מצרים מדברות שפת כנען: shene'emar bayom
hahu yihiyu chamesh arim b'eretz Mitzrayim medabrot sfat Kna'an: on that day
there will be five cities in the land of Egypt speaking the
language of כנען, Kna'an, Hebrew, the language of the Jews ונשבעות להשם
צבאות venishba'ot l'Hashem Tzeva'ot and they will swear to השם Hashem the
God. So we'll end there and therefore that's what he does with
the פסוק which is not that it was talking about בית חוניו
but it was talking about חזקיה's Chizkiya attempt after the fall of
סנחריב Sancheiriv to spread acknowledgment of God and therefore it led to
actually—oh let's just read one more sentence הלכו אל אלכסנדריא שבמצרים, halchu
el Alexandria shebeMitzrayim, they went again to Alexandria but this is again
hundreds of years before חוניו, first בית המקדש ובנו מזבח והעלו עליו
לשם שמים u'banu mizbe'ach vehe'elu alav l'shem Shamayim and they brought to
the name of God שנאמר ביום ההוא יהיה מזבח להשם בתוך ארץ
מצרים. shene'emar bayom hahu yihiyeh mizbe'ach l'Hashem b'toch eretz Mitzrayim. Okay to
be continued tonight at 7:00 as we wrap up the מסכתא. masechta.